When you open the Gnome Well project in Unity,
you’ll see several main folders.
Each has specific purpose in how Unity organizes and
run the game
Build is for Exported game builds, Library holds Unity’s cache
and Assets is the Main game folder
Inside the assets, we have App Resources for Fonts, UI icons, shared assets, Gnome for Prefabs, animations, and scripts for the gnome.
Scripts for Game logic like Rope, GameManager, CameraFollow, Settings for Input, Graphics presets.
In short, inside every folder, everything is organized by purpose.
Knowing how to navigate Unity’s interface is one thing. Creating an entire game with it is another
The way that we’ll build this game is as follows
First, we’ll create the gnome, using temporary
stick-figure images.
With the rope, Gnome, and input system in place, we can begine actually creating the game itself
We’ll implement the traps and
the treasure, and start playing the game proper.
From there, it’s just matter of polish: the Gnome’s sprites will be replaced with more complex ones
Now, let’s get started
Here, i already created the project, downloaded the assets from the repository, unzipped them into the appropriate folder in my project, and imported the prototype Gnome assets
My Gnome’s Well development process
will be divided into three phases
The phase one is setting up
In phase one, we created the project named “Gnome Well”
and promote that, prototype Gnome assets
We added Sprites to the
Scene
And with the assets imported, we move
into assembling our gnome
We opened the folder, we just
brought into the Unity
then dragged each sprite directly into the
Scene view or the Hierarchy window.
At this point, we saw
six different sprites appear in our scene
At first, pieces were all there,
but they weren’t place together.
Now our Gnome looks part
We give it some physics so it could interact
In the Inspector, we add Component, searched for
Rigidbody 2D, and added it so, this gave each sprite gravity
and collision capabilities.
We drag the Rope into the scene
and give ourselves more control over the rope
system later
The moment of truth, We hit the play button at the
top of Unity to see it all come to life.
Here’s a line should streched from the gnome
to a point above, simulating the rope’s anchor.
The gnome dropped down, hung from the rope, and swayed with that
floppy we were going for
Setting Up Unity Remote for Testing
Now, the game scene have mirrored to my phone
Adding tilt control
We wanted the Gnome to swing naturally
when tilting the phone
To do this, we wrote scripts:
InputManager, and Swinging script
InputManager inputs accelerator input and
reads the input the InputManager values and apply
physics force to the body.
Swinging to apply sideway force
to the Gnome’s rigidbody.
Controlling the Rope
(Extend and Extract)
We created UI button, name it down, and
anchor it to the bottom-right
We also created UI button, name it Up and,
anchor it to the bottom-right beside the Down button.
We added IU button to make
the rope longer or shorter.
For the ‘Up’ button, we made it affect
Rope.isDecreasing instead.
Making the Camera
follow the Gnome
Without the camera, the Gnome
disappears as the rope extend
We select the Camera, add a script named “CameraFollow”
and drag the Gnome’s body to the camera follow
Coding the Gnome
The Gnome needed to show
particles effects when damaged like
Lose limbs and
spawn bloody fountains.
Track whenever its
holding treasure
That is why we write
BodyPart script for individual parts
To write Gnome.cs script
for overall gnome behavior
It should show Track states for alive, dead
and holding treasure.
It also handles damage and effects
and runs DestroyGnome() to detach limbs and
spawn fountains/ghost.
Setting up Game Manager
The Game Manager is the brain
of the Gnome’s Well game.
Game Manager keeps track of the
gnome, treasure, traps, and exit.
It handles spawning a new gnome
at the start point.
Resetting object like treasure
Handling win or loss, prepare,
we create a script a Resettable script.
So, object like Treasure can
reset themselves.
We also create a GameManager script
To spawn Gnome at Start Point, attach
the Rope, and set the Camera to follow it and many more
Removing the
Old Gnome
When a Gnome dies or the game restarts, the old Gnome
should stay in the well
But stop being
“the player”.
Killing a Gnome
When a gnome dies, we wanted both
gameplay logic and effect
And keeps the camera focused on the
death spot for a moment.
Preparing the scene
Before running everthing, we
added scene setup object
We create a Start Point GameObject which is
a yellow capsule icon in the scene
The game manager spawn
gnome here
Adding traps
Traps needed to be flexible, so instead of
writing custom script for each
We made a generic solution
We create a SignalOnTouch.cs script and
when an object tagged “Player” collide
It fires a UnityEvent
Adding a background
To polish visuals, we added a
temporary background.
Resize it with
React tool
Now, there’s a background instead of
Unity’s default blue
Now, winning required two objects:
Treasure and Exit
We uses SignalOnTouch to call GameManager
to Gnome’s holdingTreasure sprites
If gnome is holding treasure
then it is victory.
Polishing the game
In this phase, we’ll be adding new sprites for the gnome,
improving the look of the background.
And adding particle effects that improve the
look of the game
Updating Gnome’s Art
GnomeParts folder contains
two subfolders:
Alive and Dead.
We’ll start with Alive
Double click the Gnome prefab
Select the body part of the gnome
like the left leg or the head
Then start changing each of them with
the part of the Alive Folder
Creating the background
To polish visual, we added temporary background
which is the background Brown
But now, we will also be adding a blue background
and a red background
And adjust their position to create
the side walls and the foreground.
The bottom of the well
Drag the bottom sprite and follow it
at the bottom of the well
Add sandy sprites on both sides
of the well
Adjust position to line up with the walls.
Place the treasure sprite in
the middle of the sand dune.
Updating the
Gnome’s Interface
After setting up the basic UI elements,
we create the Gameplay menu
And set it to stretch
across the screen
Next, we create the Game Over screen,
add the You Win text
and position the New Game button
to restart the game
We connect the GameManager to the
UI elements to handle visibility and functionality
Lastly, we add a Pause button on top-right
of the screen
and test the entire setup to
ensure everything works seamelessly.
Invisibility mode
We first made it as a
child of the Canvas
Toggle the UI element for invisibility,
position it in the top-left corner
And label it “Invicible” so
we can see it
In the toggle’s Value Changed event,
link it to GameManager gnome invicible
Play the game, toggle the Invicible checkbox,
and confirm the Gnome no longer dies from the traps.
After applied these changes
We now have polished the game with updated visual
from the Gnome
custom backgrounds, and
cleaner user interface.
The invicibility mode makes testing much quicker,
and with the Game Over screen
New restart functionality
Players can easily reset and
continue their adventure
So how to test
Open the project
in the Unity
Run the MainScene from the scene
Use the on-screen buttons to extend
and extract rope
And the goal is, to collect the treasure
then return to the top.
So the issue and improvements
Rope sometimes
extend too far
and respawn can cause rope length bugs.
And win on lose menus need polish
like text, and animation.
While the background arts and sprites are
placeholder, needs improvement visuals.
So, for the closing credits, the developer is
yours truly, Chelse Leigh Pascua
And the documentors are
Antonio, and De Luna
That’s all
Thank you.